History of the Written Word: Pages from the Past, 2400 BCE-1920 CE Z4 .H58
Lilly Library
History of the Written Word: Pages from the Past
2400 BCE-1920 CE
Lilly Library
Society of Foliophiles
Z4 .H58
1 linear foot 4 volumes
The History of the Written Word: Pages from the Past, 2400 BCE-1920 CE, consist of a collection of original leaves from rare books and manuscripts in limited portfolio sets.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquisition information unknown
Biographical Note
The Society of Foliophiles formed in the early 1920's to discuss special collections and book collecting. In an attempt to make collecting more financially attainable, the Society began to collect manuscript leaves and fragments and assemble them into thematic portfolios for sale.
Scope and Contents
The set includes examples of early printed leaves, manuscript leaves, as well as a Babylonian clay tablet and cylinder seal, Egyptian papyri, etc. Each leaf is mounted on a black sheet of heavy paper (51 x 33 cm.). Leaves are housed in four black leather, drop-front clamshell cases.
"This is collection no. ... in Portfolio Set I: History of the Written Word: Only 20 numbered sets have been issued. When this edition is completed, it obviously ends this series for all time"--limitation leaf (laid-in volume 1).
Lilly Library's set numbered 14 and signed by Foliophiles director, Alfred Stites, on the limitation leaf Lilly Library's copy lacking the prospectus with descriptive table of contents.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged roughly chronologically.
Manuscripts (Papyri); Cuneiform tablets; Illumination of books and manuscripts; Writing -- History
- Title sheet with wax stamp and limitation statement, undated (Volume 1)
- Babylonian clay tablet with cuneiform characters, ca. 2500 BCE (Volume 1)
- Babylonian cylinder seal with Sumerian inscription; accompanied by a portion of clay which shows the inscription in relief, ca. 1700 BCE (Volume 1)
- Egyptian scarab with hieroglyphics. Accompanied by a portion of clay which shows sign of the scarab in relief, ca. 1000 BCE (Volume 1)
- Fragment of an Egyptian papyrus, Book of the Dead, 18th to 20th Dynasty, approx. 1500-1100 BCE (Volume 1)
- Leaf from a manuscript Koran, probably Egyptian in origin, most likely of the 16th century (Volume 1)
- Vellum leaf, Officium Beate Marie Virginis, by an Italian scribe, 12th century (Volume 1)
- Leaf from Los Virtuosos Varones, a Portuguese manuscript on the nobility of the Portuguese aristocracy, ca. 1450 (Volume 1)
- Leaf (S4) from Infortiatum de Tortis, a large, very beautiful law book printed by Baptista de Tortis in Venice, type is bold gothic, 1495; 42 x 28 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf from a rare breviary (called "Portiforium," or handbook) adapted to the distinctive service of Salisbury Cathedral. Printed in London by John Kyngston and Henry Sutton, 1555; 22 x 16 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf from a Hebrew Bible. The books of the Major Prophets, Joshua, Judges, Samuel and Kings, printed in Hebrew by Robert Estienne (or Stephanus), son and successor of the more famous Henri Estienne, at Paris, 1544; 25 x 18 cm. (Volume 1)
- Fragment from an Arabic papyrus, 800-900 (Volume 1)
- Fragment from a Greek papyrus, ca. 100 BCE-100 CE (Volume 1)
- Leaf from Fascuculus Mirre, Delft, Roelant Bollaert, ca. 1500 (Volume 1)
- Vellum leaf from the Dutch Book of Hours, written in the middle of the 15th century; 15 x 11 cm. (Volume 1)
- Vellum manuscript leaf from a German religious work, written in an upright, careful gothic German, ca. 1450; 15 x 11 cm. (Volume 1)
- Vellum leaf (Fi) from a printed Book of Hours, probably French in origin (with woodblock border and hand-painted blue, red and gold initial letters), 1525; 16 x 8 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf from Vocabularius Praedicantium sire Variloguus, printed in Strassburg by Georg Hasner, 1488; 20 x 14 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf from the Nüremberg Chronicle, printed by Anton Koberger, 1493; 43 x 30 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf from De Imitatione Christi of Thomas A Kempis, printed by Caspar Hochfeder at Nüremberg, 1494; 30 x 22 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf (I) from In Psalterium Expositio, by Cassiodorus, 1491; 29 x 21 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf from the Chronicarum Supplementum of Jacobus Philippus Bergomensis (Foresti), an Augustinian friar; printed by Bernadinus de Benaliis, at Venice, 1486; 32 x 22 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf (C4) from the Opus Trivium, by Jean (John) Bromyard, an English theologian. Printed by Nicolas Wolff at Lyons, 1500; 20 x 13 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf (2[rum]3) from A Digest of Civil Law, by Andrea Torresano of Asolo, 1491; 43 x 29 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf from The Propositions of Aristotle, a book of excerpts in Latin from the writings of Aristotle. Printed in Venice by Joannes and Gregorius de Gregoriis, 1493; 22 x 16 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf (O2) from Gemma Vocabulorum, printed in Deventer by R. Pafraet, 1495; 21 x 14 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf (ii2) from a Latin version of the Bible, printed in Venice by Hieronymus de Paganini, 1497; 16 x 12 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf (FF4) from the first illustrated edition of Horace, printed by John Gruninger in Strassburg, 1498; 31 x 21 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf (e2) from Stultefera Navis, the Latin version of the famous satirical German poem, Das Narrenschiff, or Ship of Fools, by Sebastian Brant; printed by Bergman von Olpe at Basle, 1498; 21 x 15 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf from Biblia Latina, an incunable work printed in Venice by Reynsburch and Novimagio, 1478; 32 x 21 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf (p. 39) from Fasciculus Temporum, an early outline of history from the creation of the world to about 1480, by Werner Rollewinck; this leaf is from the 5th edition of Erhard Ratdolt, which he brought out in Venice, 1485; 32 x 22 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf from Postilla Super Psalterium, Hugo de Sancto Caro; printed in Nüremberg by Anthoni Koberger, 1498; 33 x 22 cm. (Volume 1)
- Leaf (r3) from Arbor Scientiae, by Raimond Lull; Barcelona. Includes some ms notes, 1505, August 22; 29 x 21 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (d2) from the Chronicon of Sigebert of Gembloux; printed by Henri Estienne (Henry Stephanus) at Paris, 1513; 22 x 16 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (L) from Aeneis Vergiliana, printed by Jacobus Sacon of Lyons, 1517; 33 x 22 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf from the Commentaries on Boetius, printed by Zanotus de Castelliono for Giangiacomo de Legnano and Brothers, booksellers, at Milan, 1512; 26 x 18 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf from a German manuscript-an interesting anti-Catholic theological diatribe signed by five Protestant pastors, 1551, April 3; 22 x 16 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (at top right: Fol. X) from the fourth and last edition of the mysterious Matthew's Bible, printed by Nicholas Hyll at London, 1551; 32 x 21 cm. (Volume 2)
- Another leaf (at top of page: The Epistle) from the fourth and last edition of the mysterious Matthew's Bible, printed by Nicholas Hyll at London, 1551; 32 x 21 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (N2) from Hortus Sanitatis, this particular version by Johann von Cube of Frankfort being a compilation of two others bearing the same title and published at Mainz, 1491; 32 x 20 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (O2) from Fasciculus Mirre, Delft, Roelant Bollaert, ca. 1500; 14 x 9 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (F) from Dante's Divine Comedy, with the commentary of Christoforo Landino, printed by Jacob del Burgofranco of Pavia for Lucantonio Giunta, at Venice, 1529; 29 x 21 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf from Biblia Picturis Illustrata; printed in Paris by Pierre Regnault, 1540; 19 x 12 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (Z3) from a famous theological treatise of the 16th century, being the Text of the Opinions of Master Pietrus Lombardus; printed by Jean Moylin at Lyons, 1527; 18 x 13 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (P4) from The Twelve Books of the Orations of Quintilian; printed by Pierre Vidoue and published by Jean Petit at Paris, 1527; 34 x 22 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (C3) from The Twelve Books of the Orations of Quintilian; printed by Pierre Vidoue and published by Jean Petit at Paris, 1527; 34 x 22 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (C4) from Postille Majores cum Questionibus, by Pierre Balli; printed by him at Lyons, 1525; 26 x 17 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf from The Commentaries of Bartolus de Saxoferrato on the first and second parts of the new Digest of Laws with supplemental notes by other scholars. Published at Lyons by Jacob Saccon, 1521; 39 x 28 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (S2) from Nova Legenda Angliae, from the press of Wynkyn de Worde, printed at "the Flete Strete," London, 1516; 28 x 19 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (p. 144) from a collection of minor classical authors; printed by Aldus Manutius and Andrea Torresano at Venice, 1516; 31 x 21 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (S3) from Las Quatorze Decadas de Tito Livio; printed at Saragossa by George Coci, 1520; 28 x 19 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (p. 323) from Sebastian Munster's Cosmographia Universalis; printed by Heinrich Petri at Basle, 1559; 31 x 21 cm. (Volume 2)
- Another leaf from the Commentaries on Boetius, printed by Zanotus de Castelliono for Giangiacomo de Legnano and Brothers, booksellers, at Milan, 1512; 26 x 18 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (A4) from the Saturnalia of Macrobius, by Joannes Rivius; printed by Agostino de Zanni de Portesio for Lucantonio Giunta at Venice, 1513; 31 x 21 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf from The Cornucopia of Nicholas Perottus; printed at Venice, Aldine press, 1513; 31 x 21 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (E2) from Tabulae Eclypsium; printed by Johannes Winterburger at Vienna, 1514; 31 x 20 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (Eee, p. 877) from Works of Josephus, Basle, Jerome Froben, 1554; 33 x 21 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (FF3, p. 338) from Historia de Gentibus Septentrionalibus, by Olaus Magnus, Archbishop of Upsala; this leaf is from the original Latin edition, published at Rome, 1555; 27 x 20 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (Ee.v., p. 802) from a Latin version of the Bible, printed by the heirs of Carola Guillard, relict of Claude Chevallon, at Paris, 1558; 37 x 25 cm. (Volume 2)
- Another leaf (PP5, p. 914) from Sebastian Munster's Cosmographia Universalis; printed by Heinrich Petri at Basle, 1559; 31 x 21 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (D1) from An English Book of Laws, printed by Rycharde Jugge and John Cawood, at London, 1559; 27 x 20 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (Q2, p. 230) from The History of His Own Times, by Paulus Jovius, Bishop of Nocera, printed by Michael Vascosanus at Paris, 1553; 34 x 22 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (C, p. 33) from "Commentariorum in Ordinationes Regias Castellae," a Spanish law book containing a compilation of the ordinances of Castile; printed in the shop of Dominicus à Portonariis at the expense of Vincentius à Portonariis, Salamanca, 1574; 28 x 19 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (p. 153) from the so-called "Liber Sextus" of Pope Boniface VIII; this leaf is from the edition printed at Venice, 1572; 24 x 18 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (N2, p. xcv) from a book of services for the Christmas, Holy Week, &c., with musical accompaniment, published by Matthias Gastius at Salamanca, 1570; 23 x 16 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (p. 157) from Ovid's "Metamorphoses," printed by Joan. Gryphius in Venice, 1565; 30 x 20 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (p. 86) from a work on Euclid by Nicholas Tartalea; the author's last, revised edition, printed by Curtio Troiano in Venice, 1565; 21 x 15 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (p. 83) from "A Catholike and Ecclesiasticall Exposition of the Holy Gospell after S. John," translated by Thomas Timme. Printed in London, by Thomas Marshe, 1575; 30 x 20 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (p. 95) from Plutarch's "Lives of the Noble Grecians and Romanes," translated, out of the French version of Bishop Amyot, by Sir Thomas North; printed by Thomas Vautrollier at London, 1579; 31 x 22 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf from a Roman missal, issued in accordance with the decrees of the famous Council of Trent, and printed by the heirs of Lucantonio di Giunta at Venice, 1576; 17 x 12 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (Bb3) from the life of Jesus Christ, translated into Dutch from the Latin of Ludolphus of Saxony, a Carthusian monk, and printed by Peter van Ghelen at Antwerp, 1618; 28 x 18 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf from a French liturgical ms, ca. 1500; 19 x 13 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf from a breviary (includes some ms notes), 16th century; 14 x 10 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (L2, p. 58) from Polybius, his complete history, a work by the author Polybius, and printed at Haganau by printer Johannem Secerium, 1530; 28 x 20 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (Ooo3) from De Aquitilibus, Historiae Animalium, by Gessner, printed at Zurich by Fraschover, 1555; 37 x 24 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (K4, p. 151) from the first edition of the first Latin Bible to be printed in England, the Biblia Sacra; printed by Henry Middleton, 1580; 22 x 16 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (p. 70-71) from History of Religious Orders of the early 1600's. Printed by Menier in Paris, being the second edition, 1680; 23 x 17 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (p. 128) from "A Guide to Tongues," by John Minsheu. Printed at the charges of the author for John Browne, Bookseller, London, 1617; 40 x 25 cm. (Volume 2)
- Leaf (p. 1110) from The Herball of John Gerard; printed by Thomas Johnson in London, 1633; 35 x 22 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 7) from A Display of Heraldrie, by John Guillim, printed at London by Thomas Cotes for Jacob Blome, 1638; 27 x 19 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf Nnn1 from Burton's Anatomy of Melancholy, printed at Oxford, by John Lichfield, 1632; 28 x 19 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 311) from an Italian manuscript, by Theodorus Amydenius, a lawyer in the Roman Curia, written about the middle of the 17th century; 32 x 22 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 165?) from a Spanish antiphonary, typical of the Catholic choir books of that period, particularly in Spain, 17th century; 40 x 28 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf from an Italian manuscript, by "Perlone Zipoli," a transparent anagram under which Lorenzo Lippi, the well-known painter, chose to hide his authorship, 17th century; 26 x 19 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 59) from the Workes of Benjamin Jonson, printed by Richard Bishop at London, 1640; 29 x 18 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (N4) from a book of rituals of the Anglican Church, printed at London by Robert Barker, 1639; 28 x 18 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf from the New World of Words, collected and published by Edward Phillips and printed by W.R. for Robert Harford at London, 1678; 32 x 20 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 27) from the Holy Bible, Or "Biblia Sacra" Vulgate Editionis, edited by Popes Sextus V and Clemens VIII; printed in Venice by Pezzana, 1669; 27 x 18 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 784) from Numisatum Antiquorum, an illustrated work by Ezechiel Spanhemius, printed by Daniel Elsiver at Amsterdam, 1671; 24 x 20 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 493) from the Iconologia of Cesare Ripa of Perugia, with amplifications by Giovanni Zaratino Castellini, printed by Niccolo Pezzana at Venice, 1669; 23 x 17 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 86) from Estatutos Generales de Barcelona, a book of religious statutes, brought out in Mexico, by Pedro Ocharte, 1585; 19 x 15 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 598) from Portraits et Vies des Hommes Illustres, par André Thevet; from the press of Kervert and Chaudiére, Paris, 1584; 37 x 25 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. [192]) from Martin Luther's German translation of the Bible, published by the heirs of Hans Krafft at Wittenberg, 1584; 37 x 25 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 789) from the sermons of John Calvin, translated from the French by Arthur Golding; printed by Henry Middleton for George Bishop, London, 1583; 28 x 19 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf from the King James Bible; printed by Robert Barker, London, 1611; 41 x 27 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (S2) from a New Testament in Greek, issued by the house of Elzevir at Amsterdam, 1678; 20 x 16 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 256) from the New Testament in English printed by Daniel Vervliet at Antwerp, 1600; 22 x 17 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (Aij1) from Anatome Corporis Humani, by Joanne Valverdo, an Italian translation from the author's original manual in Spanish; from the Giunta Press and published at Venice, 1586; 30 x 22 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 353/354) from the "Justinian Code," Ex Officina Vignoniana in St. Gervais, near Paris, 1602; 40 x 26 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf I1 from The Four Bookes of Husbandry, collected by Conrad Heresbach and translated by Barnaby Googe. "Imprinted at London for Thomas Wight, dwelling in Paules Churchyarde, Anno Domini, 1596", 19 x 14 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (C3) from "A Guide to Tongues," by John Minsheu. Printed at the charges of the author for John Browne, Bookseller, London, 1617; 40 x 25 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (C2) from the first King James Bible in a popular edition. Printed and published by Robert Barker, the King's printer, London, 1612; 22 x 16 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (R3) from Book of European Travels, written by George Sandys, the well-known translator of Ovid in London, 1615; 28 x 18 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (K1) from Hieroglyphica, by the Reverend Archibald Simson, a Scottish preacher, and was brought out at Edinburgh by Thomas Finlason, printer to His Majesty, 1622/1623; 19 x 15 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 98) from the Hebrew Pentateuch, printed in four volumes by Pierre de la Roviere in Geneva, 1617/1618; 22 x 17 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (Gg3) from Willliam Camden's "Annalles of Elizabeth," or rather from Darcie's translation from a French translation of Camden's original work, which was written in Latin. Printed for Benjamin Fisher in London, 1625; 23 x 17 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 83) from an Irish law book, containing the Statutes of Ireland from the reign of King Edward up to and including part of that of James I. Printed by the Society of Stationers at Dublin, 1621; 26 x 18 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (p. 285) from a miniature Elzevir, viz., the much-prized volume on France in the "Republic Series," the little pocket library of travel books that have acquired a fame in inverse ratio to their size. Printed in Leyden, 1626; 11 x 6 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf from an illuminated Persian ms, early 17th century; 20 x 12 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf (Qq2) from the Vulgate edition of the Bible printed at the celebrated Plantin Press in Antwerp, 1628; 19 x 12 cm. (Volume 3)
- Leaf from Flora Londinensis, compiled and written by William Curtis, from the 1st edition, and printed in London, 1773 (Volume 4)
- Leaf X2 from The Lessons of the Protestant Episcopal Church, compiled by Andrew Fowler and published by Blauvelt, New Brunswick, New Jersey, 1798; 14 x 9 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (p. 129) from The Doctrines and Discipline of the Methodist Episocopal [sic] Church, printed by Parry Hall, Philadelphia, 1792; 17 x 10 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (p. 245) from The Confession of Faith, Associate Reformed Chruch, printed in New York by T. & J. Swords, 1799; 22 x 13 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf 2Y2 from the Fables of Aesop, with designs on wood by Thomas Bewick, printed by E. Walker for T. Bewick and Son, Newcastle-on-Tyne, 1823; 22 x 14 cm. (Volume 4)
- Miniature leaf (p. 35) from an edition of Horace, printed from a specially designed type, and published by A. Mesnier at Paris, 1828; 8 x 5 cm. (Volume 4)
- Miniature leaf Q5 from a "History of Savoy," one of the "Republic Series" issued by the celebrated house of Elzevir at Leyden, 1634; 11 x 6 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (p. 387) from The NewYork Mirror and Ladies' Literary Gazette, the 7th volume. Printed by J. Seymour at New York, 1829 and 1830; 32 x 26 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf Q1 from Icones Veteris Testamenti, or, Illustrations of the Old Testament, from designs by Holbein. Published by William Pickering and printed by Charles Whittingham, who, with his nephew, conducted the Chiswick Press, and bears the imprint, London, 1830; 20 x 13 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf QQ1 from The Book of Gems: the Poets and Artists of Great Britain, edited by S.C. Hall, with the imprint of Saunders and Otley, London, 1837; 23 x 14 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (p. 187 of The Life and Death of Richard the Third) from the historic fourth folio of Shakespeare's plays, printed at London, 1685; 36 x 23 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (p. 743) from the 3rd edition of Christopher Saur's German Bible, printed by him at Germantown, Pennsylvania, 1776; 26 x 20 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (full page engraving) from Dryden's translation of Virgil, published by Jacob Tonson at London, 1697; 37 x 23 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf Bb1 from the Works of Shakespeare, printed and published by Bioren and Madan at Philadelphia, 1796; 17 x 11 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (engraving, "Time") from Collection of Stipple engravings, by C. Taylor; printed at "No. 10, near Castle Street, Holbern", 1786; 21 x 17 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf from an early 18th century illuminated Persian ms. The text consists of celebrated Persian poems and epics. Persia, ca. 1680-1720; 20 x 11 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (p. 127) from Constitutiones de Jurejurando, a treatise on oaths by Rabbi Moses ben Maimon, more generally known as Maimonides; edited and translated by Justus Christopher Dithmar; published by Cornelius Boutesteyn, at Leyden, 1706; 24 x 19 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (p. 89) from The Extant Works of Clement of Alexandria, with textual emendations by Friedrich Sylburgh, and a recension of the Latin translation by Daniel Heinsius; issued by Jeremiah Schrey and Heinrich Johann Meyer, at Cologne, 1688; 36 x 24 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (Yyyyyyy1, p. 639, includes some ms. marginalia) from Parliamentary Acts passed during the reign of William III of England, and printed by Charles Bill and the Executrix of Thomas Newcomb, printers to His Majesty, at London, 1695-1698; 28 x 18 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (p. 405) from Dryden's Translation of Virgil, published by Jacob Tonson at London, 1697; 37 x 23 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (J1, p. 218) from a Latin manuscript entitled Candidum Puritatis Lilium. A treatise on logic written by one Julianus Antonius a Jaurigui in Guatemala, and "most worthily consecrated" to D. Aloysius Gonzaga, 21 x 16 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf from Tables of Logarithms For All Numbers 1 to 102,100, With Other Tables. By William Gardiner, and printed in London by G. Smith, 1742; 29 x 24 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (E1) from The Sonnets of Antonmaria Salvini, issued at Florence, by the press of H.R.H. The Grand Duke of Tuscany, 1728; 27 x 19 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (Ff2, p. 227) from Lucan's Pharsalia in the original, edited, with notes, by Richard Bentley, the foremost classical scholar of his time. Printed at the private press of Horace Walpole at Strawberry Hill, 1760; 29 x 23 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (p. 61-62) from The Book of Wisdom and Lies, by Oliver Wardrop. Printed at the Kelmscott Press for Bernard Quaritch, London, 1894; 21 x 14 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf from A Rackham Illustration from "Tales founded on the Plays of Shakespeare" by Charles and Mary Lamb; printed by J.M. Dent & Co. at London, 1909; 23 x 16 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (p. 65) from A Bruce Rogers Folio, a limited edition of Sir Thomas More's "Utopia," printed in New York at the Rudge Press, 1937; 26 x 17 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf from The Great Paritta, a translation in Burmese on a "palm leaf book." The colophon states that this translation was completed on the 7th waxing of the month of Tawthalin of the Burmese year 1237, 1875, September; 47 x 5 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (p. 80) from the first printed translation in Irish of the Old Testament. The title page runs as follows: "The books of the Old Testament, translated into Irish by ... Doctor William Bedel..." Printed in London, the edition being limited to five hundred, 1685; 24 x 19 cm. (Volume 4)
- Leaf (Xxx2, p. 263) from a Scotch law book, entitled, "Observations on the Acts of Parliament, made by King James I to King Charles II," by Sir George Mackenzie. Printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson at Edinburgh, 1686; 30 x 19 cm. (Volume 4)